Hello and welcome. Today we're working on how to do Monte Carlo simulation in Excel.
Now I'm just trying to show you the easiest example I can show you.
And so this is a little income statement. So sales and variable cost and fixed cost
and you'll end up with a profit, hopefully, right? So sales minus variable cost minus fixed cost
gives us a profit or it could be a loss. Now to do Monte Carlo simulation, we need to know
the mean and we need to know the standard deviation of some numbers or group of numbers.
And so at Monte Carlo simulation says, look, instead of just doing one, let's do it a thousand times
or here I'm going to show you how to do it ten thousand times. It's just as easy to do it five
hundred or a thousand or ten thousand in Excel. So let's get started. Here's what we're going to do
with the estimate. We're going to use a function called the norm inverse. So the norm.inv, the
probability, I want to randomize this number for the probability. So I've got rand, R-A-N-D is a
function in Excel and I need to open the bracket and close the bracket. And what we'll have is this
number will be randomized from zero to one. And then because it's in this function, we're going to say,
we're going to use the mean and we're going to use the standard deviation and hit OK.
And we have estimated our sales. Now I can copy this down. I can copy the variable cost and the
fixed cost. So let's check the fixed cost. It's based on the mean of 150 and the standard deviation
of 15,000. And what will happen is you'll notice every time we enter something, every time we change
a formula or type something in, these numbers will randomize and come up with a new set of numbers.
So for example, we'll take 708 minus the 356 minus the 176. We'll hit enter and those three numbers
will update automatically, but the formula will still stay. 6, 16, 338, 130, and then 147 right now
is our profit calculation. So here's what we're going to do. We're going to say, OK, the 10,000 simulation,
this is simulation zero, and I'm going to point to the here now at 74,000. Every time we hit enter,
it's going to update and randomize again. So this is called a volatile function. So what I want to do
is I want to do a column for 10,000. So I have zero right here. And what I'm going to do is on the home
ribbon, I'm going to go to the right here and do a series. The series I want is in a column. I want
it to go up by one. So the step value is one. I want it to stop at 10,000. So I'm going to hit OK.
And so you see what I have now is I've got 10,000 cells in a column and it's numbered one through 10,000.
So what I'm going to do, here's a little trick to do Monte Carlo simulation. Anything you can estimate,
you can do Monte Carlo simulation. Sounds super fancy, but it's not really. Here's what happens.
I'm going to highlight this entire column with the cells to the right. I'm going to go to the data
ribbon. And then do you see this what if analysis? We're going to do a data table. So the data table,
we could put two different inputs, a row and a column. Here I've got a column, but I don't want
it to use new numbers. I want it to just recalculate. So I'm going to use a blank cell.
I'm pointing to a blank cell. You see there's nothing in there. I want to hit OK. And it'll
take just a second to refresh. And what we'll see is that this number, this original profit is
then recalculated and simulated 10,000 times. Now, the cool thing about this is we can now
highlight this and do the mean and the min and the max and figure out what's our risk of loss.
And that what we're worried about that, we do not want to lose money or we want the risk of losing
money to be really small. So I'm going to select this entire column and I'm going to name it. This is
called a named range. So I can go to formulas and name manager and I can say, I want a new and I'm going
to call this profit. So I've just named this range to be called profit. So there it is.
We see it's G4 through G10,003. All right. So now for the mean, the mean is the average.
So the average, and I can just start typing in profit and you see it says, hey, do you want this
profit right there? Yes, I do. And you see it selects everything in blue. So what is the average
of all those profit numbers? Well, it's 109,789. What is the minimum? Well, the min of profit
is 173. And that's a loss because it's in parentheses. That's a negative number. So we're worried about a
loss. There's a negative. The worst of all the 10,000 is negative 173. So $173,000 loss.
For max, we can do the maximum number of profit. Well, that's 433. Do you see the minimum change a
little bit? Well, what percent of the time of these 10,000 do we have a loss? So here's what I want to
do. I want to go to, I'm just going to do the number as a general number. I'm going to do count
ifs. Count ifs is a function. And it's going to say, what's the range and what's my criteria? Well,
the range is profit, comma, and then my risk of loss is anything. I need to start with a quote
less than zero. And quote again, close my brackets. And it says 740 times out of the 10,000
is how many times we're less than zero. So that would be the 749 losses. And you see every time
it's going to update, we know this. If I divide this by the 10,000, then I'll have some kind
of estimate. I need to make it a percentage. So about 7% of the time we would lose money in
this example. Now, if we change this, we change fixed costs from 150 to 200,000, the risk of loss
will go up. So now it's 21%. We're worried about the risk of loss. And that's how you do
the Monte Carlo simulation, 10,000 simulations. Excel can do it.